Okay, so the story
...】】}
so far is that 200,000 years ago,
.????..??..??..??..??..??..??..???
we humans, Homo sapiens,
]?..??..???
we were born in Africa.
...
And then about 50,000 years ago,
在...????????????????????????????????????????????????
because of climate change,
?
we started to spread around the world, okay?
我们开始在世界各地扩散，好的？
We went into Europe, then into Asia,
?
then we crossed the Bering Strait into North America
然后我们跨过白令海峡进入北美，随后又跨过巴塞尔海峡到达南美。
and South America. Then Asia went to Australia, okay?
再来，亚洲到达了...??
And 50,000 years ago, there's about a million of us all around the world.
在...??…??????????????????????????????????????????????????
And the argument that I'm making you, that
.???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???…??…………………………………………………………………??……… ? …… ..??………………………? …..??……??? …..??…??………………………………………………
I've made to you in this class is that from the very beginning,
???
we were religious, okay?
]}
We know from the Ice Age cave paintings.
???
We know because of places like the Great Barrier Reef.
]}
Go play at Tepe and kind of
Go play at Tepeand kind of
Høøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøø is
animistic, meaning we believe
that we all come from one source,
that we all comefrom one source,
the Mother Goddess, and
...
we are all the children of the Mother Goddess,
including animals, plants.
包括动物、植物
And because of this,
...
we were a very compassionate people
我们是一个非常有爱心的人们
that were egalitarian.
我们是一个平等的士兵
There was no difference between men and women.
没有男女之分。
That was peaceful.
那是个好时光
We were violent.
我们是有点儿的！
There was some violence, but we didn't really fight wars.
...
And we were artistic.
We celebrated the Mother Goddess through paintings
...
and through artwork.
和通过艺术作品。
And now the question then is,
现在的问 题是……
if we were like this
如果我们在这几天里...??
for most of human history,
]}We need to translate cues 35 and 36. They are: [35] if we were like this [36] for most of human... Wait we need to parse: The cues: [35] if we were like this [36] for most of human history, but we need to produce translations array with two strings. Use Chinese terms. Let's translate:
how is it that today we have war,
??
private property, and violence against the Mother Goddess?
And patriarchy, where men make all the rules
...
and women have little agency and power.
如果我们在这几天里...??
And so this week I will explain to you how this happened.
Okay? So in today's class,
??
we will discuss really the height of this civilization.
And this is what the anthropologist
...
Maria Gimbertas called Old Europe.
Okay? So to begin the story,
??
I want to tell you what
...
we discovered in terms of linguistics.
??
So for many hundreds of years,
many people have speculated
many people havespeculated
that maybe English, German,
翻译：
Greek, Latin,
希腊语，拉语，
all came from the same language that's been lost to us.
全是从同一语言而来。
This is a language we call Proto -Indo -Hungarian.
译文1
Proto -Indo -European. And
译文2
through decades of research,
通过几十年的研究，
linguists have been able
to conclusively prove
译文1
that all these languages that
译文2
we speak in Europe, okay, all come from the same mother language,
我们在欧洲说的，好的，来自同一母语的...??
the first language. But not only that, but also Iranian,
?? ?? ?? 中文 ?? ?? ?? ?? -?? ?? 我们……
and Indian,
和印度，
okay, Hindi, okay,
好吧，...??
all come from Proto -Indo -European.
??
So the question, so, okay, does that make sense to you guys?
...??
All right? So
we know this because there are many words
我们知道它有多种词语
that sound the same in many languages, okay?
...
So for example, father in English is father, right?
比如说，英语里的父亲是father，没错吧？
But in Latin it's pater, okay?
但在拉丁语里，父亲是pater?
That's where we get the word paternity, okay?
那时我们得到的就是“paternity”这个词，好的？
From the father. Greek,
??
pateris, Persian, padar, Hindi in India, pita, okay?
pateris，波斯语，padar，印度的印地语，pita，好的？
So the word father seems to come from just one word in all these different languages.
所以，父亲的词语来自于这几种语言的单词。
Then you look at the word mother, okay?
然后看一下单词母亲，好的？
Mother, matar, matara, madar, mat, okay?
母亲，母语??
Also sounds very similar.
...
So again, for hundreds of years,
people have speculated that,
人们曾经常推测，
um, um,
嗯，嗯，
um, there is just one language.
嗯，嗯……
And if you look at this map, okay?
...
So for example, the English word for two, okay?
The number two. You can draw a schematic
...
that shows you how all these languages,
那展示了你如何把所有这些语言，
the word two, derived just from one word, dua, okay?
该词语的两字由一词二语得来，
So languages have been able to piece
语言已能拼出
together this Proto -Indo -European language.
...
We've also been able to figure out how this language spread, okay?
So there are two hypothesis.
...
Either the language spread from Turkey,
第[91]句：从土耳克语种或从乌克兰语种开始，
Anatolia or from Ukraine, okay?
?
Basically Russia. And
we know it spread all around the world, okay?
我们知道它已经在全世界传播，好的？
So basically all of Europe and including Iran
所以，基本上所有的欧洲和包括伊朗的...
and India, okay?
...
So this is the first language of all these languages, languages that we see.
we speak today in most of Asia and all of Europe.
...
So any questions so far?
All right. Now,
好的，开始。
the problem for linguists is
语言学家们的工作是：
how do you piece together the language, okay?
语言学家们怎样把语言拼成？
Because this language is lost to us.
因为这门语言已失去。
So this language is lost to us.
And so what linguists did, okay, and this is a very slow process is,
可归为此类??
they basically looked at all the words that
他们看了所有的...
seemed to come from the same word in different languages.
...
What they discovered is that there's certain words
that are distinct to the first language.
那是第一种语言独有的词汇。
So words like bull, cow,
于是，单词如牛、羊...
ox, ram,
ox, ram
eel, lamb,
eel
pig, piglet, sour milk,
...
why, herds, field,
dog, shear wool,
dog
textiles, scratch plow, oxen,
textiles
yoke, grain, shaft, furrow,
轭、谷物、轴、犁、
wrestling, grinding, pestle, households, okay?
摔跤、研磨、杵、家户、
What do you guys notice about these words?
你们看到这些词有什么感悟吗？
Do you see patterns in these words?
你们看得出字词里有点儿
What patterns do you see in these words?
什么样的词语有点儿？
Okay, so what these words tell us is the culture and lifestyle
好的，先前的那句…
of the Proto -Indo -Europeans, okay?
Does that make sense? So from these words, we're able to figure out four things
about the Proto -Indo -Europeans.
...
The first thing is that
unlike other cultures,
不同于其他文化，
these people have a word for wheel.
这些人有个词语
In fact, they have five different words for wheel.
...
And what this tells us, what we can guess
that these people, whoever they are, they invented the wheel.
这些人，谁是他们，发明了轮子。
doesn't make sense. They have words for wheel and other cultures don't.
它们没有出现过。”
So they were the first to invent the wheel.
133 ... … ... … … ... … … - ? ?… … … … … … ... … - ? ? 1…… … … {
Second is that they have words for dairy products,
]}We need to translate cues 133 and 134. The previous context: we have translation for 133? Wait we have previous translations? The previous context shows translations for 133 and 134? Actually we have previous context lines 133 and 134:
cow milk. And this is important.
cow milk ... ... ...
Why? Do you guys know why this is important? Why is this strange?
...
Yes, okay, so they were raising livestock, okay?
Okay, what makes it strange is that for most of human history,
...
we were lactose intolerant.
we were lactoseintolerant.
Meaning we did not have the ability to drink milk.
翻译1
So these people, not only did they invent the wheel,
]}We need to translate cues 140 and 141. We have previous translation?We need to produce JSON with translations array. Let's translate. 140:
but they changed their system.
但他们改变了自己的系统。
Biological system so that they became lactose tolerant.
生物系统使他们变成了乳糖耐受者。
They now have the capacity to drink milk, okay?
...
Does that make sense? So whatever these people are,
are the first people to drink cow milk.
Okay, the second characteristic,
...
sorry, the third characteristic is they really don't have
抱歉，第三个特征是他们真的没有
that many agricultural terms.
翻译后可用??????????????????????????????????????????
Okay? So maybe they farmed, but
they weren't focused on farming, okay?
...
Whereas other cultures were focused on farming.
其他文化聚焦于农耕。
Okay? That's the third thing.
好的，算作第3点。
The fourth thing is they have words for horse.
第154条：...
And this is important because this tells us that they were first to
第155条：...
domesticate the horse, meaning that they could control the horse.
第156条： 养育了...
Okay? This is important because throughout history,
第157条： 养育...
horses, if they see a human, they run away, okay?
马匹若见人，跑开，好的？
Because that's the best way to survive.
If you see someone coming, you run away.
如果你看到有人来，跑开。
This, this is what we're going to call excitability, okay?
这就是我们要说的兴奋性。
Horses are excited.
马匹兴奋...
So it took thousands of years for these people,
...
the Proto -Indo -Europeans, to domesticate the horse,
the ... ………………………………………………
which means they could ride the horse.
...………???……
Okay, does that make sense? So we don't know who these people were,
...…………………………………………………
but based on their language, we're able to guess four things, okay?
但根据他们的语言，我们可以猜测四件事，好的？
So this is a theory. Now what's interesting is
这是一种理论。现在有趣味的就是…
that archeologists start to dig up, okay, and they dig up things.
考古学家们开始挖掘，好的，…
And they start to discover the linguists were right,
???
okay? By saying the language, the language had four hypotheses. And
the archeologists were able to provide evidence this is true,
???
okay? The most exciting thing is that
好的？最激动的事是…
for the past five to ten years, advances in genetics,
好的，…
DNA technology, we've been able to look at the DNA of these skeletons. And
DNA技术，我们已经能查看这些骨骼的DNA。然后…
we've been able to confirm a lot of these hypotheses,
we've been able to confirma lot of these hypotheses,
okay? Does that make sense? So what I'm,
???
what I'm telling you is for the longest time,
we guessed that the Proto -Indo -Europeans existed.
...
But now we have conclusive, conclusive, scientific evidence
that they did exist and who they were, okay?
...
Does that make sense? All right.
???
So wheels, okay?
??
So again, they have five, five different words for wheels.
And we're able to know from the archeological evidence,
...
the wheels were invented about 3500 BC,
okay? In this area, okay, basically Russia.
...
And because wheels are part of Proto -Indo -European,
then this language,
???
whoever starts to first speak it must have been speaking it after 3500 BC,
??
okay? Does that make sense? All right?
...
There aren't that many agricultural terms in Proto -Indo -European,
okay? We have a lot of words for Proto -Indo -European.
...
milk okay to milk sour milk buttermilk cheese cow okay
milk
so whoever these people were dairy products were very important part of their culture
...
and their diet this is DNA DNA evidence that
shows us that these people
显示了这些人
who if we call the Anaya okay these people call
他们的名字叫…
the Anaya they were able to develop hormones
...
that allowed them to be
lactose tolerant okay in
乳酸...
about 4400 BC very few people could drink milk
...
and by the time of the Anaya about a thousand years later they could basically all drink milk
在安纳雅时期大约一千年后，他们基本上都能喝牛奶
and because
]}We need to translate cues 203 and 204. Provide JSON with translations array of two strings. Ensure Chinese natural. Use terms:
they could drink milk what happens to their body you guys
...
know what's the difference you guys know what's the difference if you drink milk exactly okay
so we know from the evidence that
...
these people are taller than everyone else in fact these people
翻译1
because they drink milk and
...
they eat a lot of protein they
???
were on average 20 centimeters taller than farmers
?
okay it doesn't make sense you guys okay yeah go ahead
好的，它没有意义，你们好吧，接着说
okay okay okay so
好的，好的，好的，咱们来吧！
the drink the milk we drink today is very different from the milk
...
that they drink before you understand the milk they drink before came from cows
that were raised in grassland so
那在草原里饲养的，随后……
it's all in the grassland so it's all natural the milk we drink today comes from cows
]}We need to translate cues 216 and 217. Provide JSON with translationsarray of two strings. Ensure Chinese natural. Let's translate: cue 216:
that are raised in factories and
那在工厂里养的，接着注入大量药物
we inject a lot of drugs and
we inject a lotof drugs and
hormones into these cows did you understand
???
no no no no if you drink milk a lot your bones will be healthier
no no no no if you drink milk alot your bones will be healthier
and you'll grow taller okay that
and you'll growtaller okay that
that's just that's just biological evidence okay does that make sense
that's just that's just biologicalevidence okay does that make sense
but the milk we drink today we put a lot of chemicals into the milk
...
and the sourcing of the milk is from factories okay
and and and the reason why is we want to make the milk cheaper
??
but it's worse for you okay so
但它更好吧？
in other words if you really want to be healthy what you should do is go buy a cow
在其他词里，...??
and drink from that
]}We need to translate cues 228 and 229. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure Chinese natural. Let's translate: cue 228:
cow okay do you understand all right okay
...???..??..............................................………………………..…..………………..?…..??…..?…..???…..??..???…....??……....……..?…....……..………..…..……....?…..……..?…??..???…..??……?…..???…..??..??..??..………………………………………………………………………………..
so so are we clear okay so
?…..??..…………..…..……?…..……..?…..??……..
we are clear okay so
咱们先说牛吧，明白了吗？
we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear
]}We need to translate cues 232 and 233. We have to output JSON array with two translations. Let's craft Chinese subtitles. Cue 232:
okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay
???
so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so
we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay
...
so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so
??
we are clear okay so we are clear okay
so we are clear 1500 BCE until 2200 BCE to domesticate the horse
??
because it's very hard to make horses
not run away when there's danger.
翻译结果
It doesn't make sense.
...
So this is a very long process,
翻译结果
but they were able to accomplish it.
??
The further evidence for the domestication of a horse
is we've been able to dig up skeletons. And
??
what we see is the skeletons
...
of the Anaya are different from other skeletons
and it's because they ride horses.
和...??
That changes the curvature of the skeleton.
那一段落在此处…
Does it make sense guys?
So the evidence is pretty overwhelming.
So the evidence ispretty overwhelming.
Eventually they were able
最终...
to put all the pieces together.
把所有片段拼在一起。
They were able to put the horse and the wheel together.
他们能把马和轮子组合在一起。
And as such they create the wagon.
翻译成中文：
The wagon meant they could move from place to place
?
and they became what we call nomadic pastoralists.
和………………………………………………………………………
So have you guys been to Mongolia?
...
Have you guys been to Mongolia?
你们去过蒙古吗？
Yes, same.
是的，和我一样。
But you see the way they
但你们看到他们的生活方式是...
make a living is they have like cows and sheep, right?
...
And they take the cows and
the sheep from place to place to eat the grass, right?
...
And they're able to do that because
they're able to put all the belongings into a wagon
他们可以把所有的物品装进一辆车里
and move from place to place.
...
Okay, does that make sense? So these are the people
who
...
were the first speakers of Proto -Indo -European.
翻译后...
And eventually, they're able to spread the word.
最终，他们把词语传播开来。
They spread their language all around the world.
他们把语言传播到全世界。
Okay from Europe to India to Iran.
好的，从欧洲到印度再到伊朗。
It doesn't make sense guys. Now the question is okay we're able to confirm
它们没能给出一个好句子。
that these people actually existed and
...
we are able to confirm that
they did spread the language around the world.
他们把语言传播到全世界。
Now the question the debate is how do they do so?
Okay and there's two sides to the argument.
好的，且有两种观点。
argument. The first side,
OK?
the first side believes
第一方认为
these people were conquerors.
这些人是征服者。
Okay, so think Genghis Khan and the Mongols.
好的，想想成吉斯·汗和蒙古人。
They went around, they were able to spread their language by conquering other people.
他们四处奔走，能把语言传播到各方。
Okay, so think Genghis Khan and the Mongols.
好的，先前往成吉斯·汗和蒙古人。
Think of the European conquest of North
想想欧洲对北美和南美的征服，英、法、德等国去往北美和南美，消灭当地人。
and South America where the English and the Spanish and
想法...
the French went to North and South America and eradicated the local population.
...
Okay, so that's the first belief.
好的，先前…
The second belief is that it was not violent.
...
Okay, it was just cultural diffusion,
meaning I came to your country or your village
我来到你们的国家或村庄，
and I was able to influence you
我能在此处发出影响力，
and convince you that my language is superior.
又能给我方言语的方能。”
Okay, so we call this cultural diffusion.
好的，先前…
So think of English where, okay,
...
China has not been conquered by the West,
but we want to learn English because we think that
...
learning English will give us more life opportunities.
Okay, does that make sense? So there's two sides of the debate,
...
either one of conquest or one of cultural diffusion.
翻译1
And this debate went on for a long time.
翻译2
Okay, and
翻译…
for most of the time we believed it was cultural diffusion.
在大部分时间里我们认为它是文化传播。
So we believe that it was cultural diffusion. But
在此时此刻，先前的古代人们先前…
now for the past five to ten years,
]}We need to translate cues 305-307. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use preferred terms. Let's translate: cue 305:
we have overwhelming
...
DNA evidence that it was in fact conquest.
DNA证据显示它确实是一次征服。
It was a genocide. It was a violent conquest.
它是一次大规模的繁复…
And this is what I will show you next class.
...
Okay, but
in today's class what I will show you is the Europe before the conquest.
...
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, and then
next class we will look at how Europe was conquered.
下节课我们将看欧洲是如何被征服的。
Okay, so this is the first class. This is how Europe was conquered and how it was changed because of a conquest.
好的，先说一说这场说服的第一节课。
Okay, any questions so far?
Okay, so there's a quick question.
好的，先说一条快速的问句。
The question is, what's the difference between conquest and diffusion?
...
Okay, the answer is this.
If I conquer a country, conquer you, I eradicate your genes.
如果我征服了某国，我就把它的国民们的命运归于此，命运归于此…
I kill you, okay?
...
Therefore your genes do not come into the present day.
因此你的基因已不再出现于今日。
Whereas if it's diffusion, your genes are still around.
而若是扩散，便是此时已有回响。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这是否已好？
So what I will show you next class is,
那么我接下来要展示的就是
sorry, a lot of these genes have been eradicated.
很抱歉，某些基因已归一百多种之中…
Therefore it must have been a violent conquest.
…
Does that make sense? Okay. All right.
...
Let's now look at Europe before the conquest.
And a lot of what we know about Europe
...
comes from a very famous anthropologist.
来自一位非常著名的人类学家。
Her name is Maria Gambates, okay?
玛丽亚·甘比塔斯的名字是…
And we'll be spending a lot of time today talking about her theories.
...
But what we know is, okay,
remember the Ice Age ended about 12,000 years ago.
记得冰河时代大约一万二千年前结束。
Okay? And this is how the planet is warming, which allows for agriculture.
好的，地球正好在此时暖化，便可种植作物。
We also know that
我们也知道，
agriculture started in Anatolia, Turkey,
农作开始于安塔利亚，土耳其。
and in Egypt and in Mesopotamia, okay?
在埃及与美索不达里亚，好的？
Basically this region.
在这片区域里
And the reason why is this place was the first to warm up,
这片地方先后先发热，先后又有好土壤，才会有…
but it also had better soil than other places, okay?
这句…
So they discovered farming in this region.
于是他们在这片地区发现了农耕。
And in about 6500 BCE,
大约公元前6500年，
this region was the first to warm up. So they started to grow. agriculture started to spread around the world, okay?
这片地区先后先发热，先后…
To Europe and then over to England.
??
Okay, does that make sense, guys?
好的，先前先后…
Okay. Another question then is,
好的，先前…
what propelled this migration from Anatolia to Europe?
什么推动了从安塔利亚到欧洲的迁移？
Can you guys guess? What would propel this migration?
你们能给我方位吗？
Hmm? Okay.
嗯？好的。
So, a good guess is war, okay?
好，先后…
But we don't have any evidence of war around this time.
但我们在那段时间没有发现战争的证据。
What's another explanation why people wouldn't move?
“可”…??
Exactly, thank you. Climate change, okay?
翻译1
The weather became a lot cooler during this time,
翻译2
make it harder for people to farm, okay?
让它更难让人们耕种，好的？
Also, they've been farming for a long time in this area, which
让我们来吧！
meant that the soil is longer as good as before,
意为土壤更長久好，
okay? So you had these massive changes, okay?
意为土壤更長久…
And then you had these massive migrations of families into Europe,
翻译1
because Europe at this time, it was becoming,
因为在此时的欧洲，变成了
the weather was becoming a lot warmer,
天气变得更暖
which allowed people to start to grow agriculture in this area, okay?
哪裡讓人們開始在此區域種植農業，對吧？
So in about 6500 BCE,
在大約公元前6500年，
people started to move from Anatolia into this area.
...
And because they were moving,
they brought with them their religion, okay?
他们带着宗教来了吗？
Remember like the religion of Goble Tepe, and kind of how they were moving, right?
记得?
The Holy Act is one of the mother goddess, giving life to everything, okay?
...
And because of that, we know that the people in this area
were mainly egalitarian, peaceful,
主要是平等的，且很平安
and artistic, okay? Does that make sense?
...
Okay, what we'll study next class
好的，下节课我们要研究的就是
is that there were two massive migrations into Europe.
两大批次的迁徙进入欧洲。
All caused by climate change.
全部因气候变化而引起。
The first migration are farmers, okay?
第一批次的农民，好的？
The second migration are pastoralists.
第二批次的牧民。
And what I will show you next class is,
翻译1
we will look at the DNA evidence, okay?
翻翻译2
So if you look at the DNA of people today,
翻译3
what you will see is that about 4500 BCE,
383: 约 4500 年前，欧洲人大约一百个字母…
most people in Europe, their genes were mixed,
? ? ? ……
most people in Europe, their genes were mixed, but the second migration was based on the genes of farmers who came from Anatolia,
? ……
as well as hunter gatherers who were there originally, okay?
作为原始的捕食者，
Does that make sense? But then after 3000 BCE,
它们在 3000 年前出现。
you have this green come in, okay?
And the green are the Yemnaya, okay?
绿点代表Yemnaya，好的？
The Proto Indo -Europeans.
原始印欧人。
And so I will show you this next class, okay?
接下来我会展示下一节课，好的？
But I want you guys to understand what happened, okay?
但我想让你们了解发生了什么，好吗？
Does that make sense? Okay, so again,
它们的确是...
this is a map of the migration, okay?
这是一张地图…
So agriculture was started in about 9,000 BCE in the Near East,
约9,000年前在近东开始种植业，土耳克...
Turkey, Anatolia, as well as Israel,
约...??…...???
Syria, Jordan, then
...
it spread from about 7,000 to Europe, okay?
它从大约7000年前传播到欧洲，好吗？
And then the purple is the Yamnaya people, okay?
紫色部分是Yamnaya人，好吗？
Who we believe were from Ukraine, in the steppes,
我们认为他们来自乌克兰的草原。
and they spread around the world.
...
Next class, we'll discuss who the Yamnaya were
下一节课我们会讨论Yamnaya人是谁，...
and how they conquered the world, okay?
下一节课…
But first, I want to look at the farmers
但先，先看一下…
who built Europe before the conquest of the Yamnaya.
...
So again, Okay.
[406] So again,Okay.
Maria Gumbutas, who
[407] Maria Gumb ...
is an anthropologist originally from Lutherania,
408：拉图尔拉尼亚的古老人类学家， 但…
but who worked at Harvard and UCLA,
408：拉图尔拉尼原始人类学家…
she's done decades of research into old Europe,
已完成十几年的研究…
okay? And her conclusion is
??…
that
...
old Europe was
conquered by the Yamnaya people,
在 里 里…
okay? And this is what we know as the Yamnaya.
}]
So this is what we know as the Kurgan hypothesis.
...
So let me explain what the Kurgan hypothesis is.
]}We need to translate cue 417:
We know the burials of
我们知道农民的葬礼与雅马纳雅人葬礼的区别。
the farmers is very different from the burials of the Yamnaya people.
...
The major difference is this.
The people who are farmers are buried together,
...
okay? But the people of the Yamnaya, they're buried alone.
Not only are they buried alone, but they're buried with weapons
...
and weapons.
和武器。
with cattle and horses.
与牛奶与马。
So what we can guess from this, okay, we don't have evidence,
在此可推测，...
but what we can guess from this is that
?
the farmers were people who
农民是那种人，
did not have private property and who
农民们的...??
were egalitarian, okay, and who were peaceful because they didn't have any weapons.
是平等的，好的，且因为没有武器而显得平和。
And the Annihiler were the complete opposite, okay.
而且是个别的！
These were warriors who
这些是...
believed in private property
...
and which was male -dominated, okay.
Does that make sense? So this is what we refer to as the Kirken hypothesis.
翻译成中文：
And for the longest time, this is something that
?】}We need to translate cues 435-437. Provide array translations. Let's translate. 435:
Maria Gumbates argued and
? We need proper Chinese. Let's produce:
she was laughed at.
翻译成...??
Why was she laughed at? Why would people laugh at her?
???????????????? ..??? …… …..??……..……………………… …… ?……..??…… ……… …… …………… ……?… ………………
She's saying like, okay, before these Annihiler came to Europe,
?……..……………………………………
Europe was a place that
欧洲是个...
was basically governed by woman
...
and it was artistic, you know, it was peaceful, it was egalitarian.
Why would people laugh at her?
...
Yeah, they don't believe in her. Why? Excuse me?
??
Yeah, yeah. First of all,
...
in universities it's the men who are professors, right?
在大学里，男生是教授，对吧？
It's the men who are scholars. So there are many men who are like,
在学术界，男生是学者，故此有许多男生为学者。
there's no way woman can be in charge.
有点儿...
They're idiots, okay.
...
Why would women be in charge?
??
They're stupid, they're useless.
It's men who are always in charge, okay.
它们是男的，时常在掌握之中，好的。
That's one reason why they laugh at her.
那是个好时机，去把它们的后面。
What's another reason why they would laugh at her?
另一个原因是他们会笑她的原因是什么？
Okay, there are also a lot of people who who believe people are violent.
好的，另外还有很多人相信人类是多么的？
We've had wars always, okay?
??
The idea for like thousand years,
Europe was peaceful can't be true
欧洲曾经和平，未必如此。
because people are violent.
因为人类已有冲突。
Humans are meant to go to war against each other.
人类本来就会互相争战。
Okay? The third reason why people would laugh at her is
好的？第三个原因是人们会因为她而笑的那一…
we think we are motivated by money, right?
好的，...…
If you don't have money, then why would you do anything?
??
Does that make sense? So,
那算得了？于是，
Maria Gumbotas had this radical idea
玛丽亚·金布塔斯有个极其...
that challenged the way
那...
that men saw the world.
...
Okay? For men, men have always been in charge.
There's always been wars,
...
and there's always been wealth and
和...
money to motivate people to work hard, okay?
...
And that's what men believe.
And Maria Gumbotas said, no, that's not true.
For thousands of years, from 6500 B.C.
...
until about 2500 B.C., 4,000 years before they were conquered,
Europe was ruled by women,
欧洲曾由女性统治，并因此而安宁、平等、艺术繁盛。
and because of that, Europe was peaceful, egalitarian, and artistic.
Okay? So this is a radical idea.
...
And again, what I will show you next class is
this idea that was laughed at for, you know,
这件事，咱们先前说过的那点儿…
decades, has now been confirmed by DNA evidence,
...
meaning that this has been proven true by science, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay, so
...
let's look at what Maria Gumbotas said.
让我们看看玛丽亚·金布托斯说了什么。
And she's written quite a few books.
她写了几本书。
These are two of her most famous. The Language of the Goddess
这些是她的两本最著名的书，语言之神女的书！“语言”…
and The Civilization of the Goddess, okay?
...
So her main theory is that Europe at that time,
所以她的主要理论是，
their main belief is in a mother goddess who gives life, gives life to everything, okay?
她的主要信念是：
And so what she did was she went
她的做法是：
and she dug up their graves to look at their art,
...
and she studied their language and their cultural practice, okay?
Does that make sense? Any questions so far?
...
Okay. So this is from The Civilization of the Goddess,
好的，来自《女神文明》
and we'll read this together, okay? And so
我们一起读这段落
this is her main argument about, Old European culture.
她的主要论点是古欧文化
And the infamous infamous infamous infamous
...
infamous infamous infamous infamous infamous infamous!
infamous! infamous!!!
...
infamous infamous infamous infamous infamous perception of all the sacredness
and mystery of all there is on earth.
...
So everything in the world is sacred
because it is blessed by the mother goddess.
因为...
If there's a mosquito,
...
don't kill that mosquito because
it has the energy of the mother goddess.
它有点儿…
If you are walking and
...
you see a bird,
a small bird, pick it up and heal it
...
because that comes from the mother goddess.
因为那来自母神的能量。
Does that make sense?
这就好吗？
This culture took deep delight in the natural wonders of this world.
...
Its people did not produce lethal weapons
or build forts in inexorable places as their successors did even
或在无穷的地方建造堡垛，像他人后继者一样，
when they were acquainted with metallurgy.
...
So in other words, they had the technology to make weapons.
所以，另一种说法是：我们有了能打工的技术，...
They had the technology to build forts and make war, but they chose not to.
...
Does that make sense? These people chose,
那算得了吗？这些人选择了，
purposely chose, not to commit violence against other people.
那点儿...??
Instead, they built magnificent tombs, shrines, and
代之以建造宏伟的坟墓、神殿与庙宇，舒适的居所于中等大小的村落中。
temples, comfortable houses in moderately sized villages,
舒适的居所…
and created superb pottery and sculptures.
??
This was a long -lasting period of remarkable creativity
这是一段长久的...
and stability in an age free of strife.
...
Their culture was a culture of art.
It doesn't make sense. They spent all their
它不太合理。他们把全部时间和精力投入到这些事物的制作上。
time and energy in producing these things.
它们…
They spent all their time and energy in producing these things. They spent all their time and energy in producing these things. They spent all their time and energy in producing art to celebrate the mother goddess and to celebrate nature and to celebrate themselves.
This was remarkably peaceful and stable.
这是一段长久的...
Does that make sense, guys? Any questions so far?
What was amazing about this culture is they invented writing.
这是一段长...
Now for the longest time, we believe that
现在，最长时间里，我们认为
the Sumerians, which we will discuss later on, the Sumerians who lived in Iraq,
萨尔米尔人，先后会谈到的...
we believe they discovered writing.
我们...
And we discovered that writing came about for economic purposes.
我们发现文字主要用于经济目的。
So for example, if you are in Sumeria
在萨尔米尔里…
and you need to build a temple,
...
what you do is you create writing.
你所做的就是生成文字。
So for example, here's a play, and I say this.
这里有个例子，给我说个…
So this is writing, right?
…
What does this mean? It means like these two people,
什么是这句的意思？它是说两个人的…
this family of two, will get two bushes of wheat
...
and two baskets of bread for their work today.
Does that make sense? So we thought that for the longest time,
那就好啦！
people created writing because or for economic purposes,
那好啦！
okay, in order to have an economy.
那好…
But what Maria Gambates has discovered is,
翻译1
no, we actually created writing before for religious purposes.
翻译2
Okay? So for example, if I have a painting, okay, and it goes like this.
翻译3
Okay, so like this. And
...
what I'm saying is the
我正在说的就是...
mother goddess blesses
我正在翻译??????????????????????????????????????????????
this sculpture
with her life
?
and with the abundance of water in nature.
和水的丰富性相伴随
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的，水的变成…
So writing is a way to communicate with the mother goddess.
写作是与母神沟通的方式。
It's a way to make divine and sacred our art.
写作 … …
Does it make sense, guys? Okay?
So these people were
??
so sophisticated, they invented writing.
Okay. Now,
OK? 先后??
I want to go over some of the cultural differences between
I want to go over some of thecultural differences between
that culture and our culture to show how stark the differences are.
那种文化与我们的文化对比，展示了差异的显著性。
Okay? So for example, in today's culture,
OK? 先后??
when we think of snake, we think of poison, danger,
right? We've been taught that snakes are dangerous.
右？我们被教蛇是危险的。
But in this culture, the snake was a symbol of life energy and regeneration.
但在这文化里，蛇是生命能量与再生的符号。
Because, you know, snakes can shed their skin, right?
因为，你知道，蛇能蜕皮，才是吧？
A most benevolent, not an evil creature.
再现一回！
Okay? So that's one major difference.
OK? 先后??
Another major difference between our culture and their culture is,
在此时刻，...
in today's world, we think that, white is good, black is bad.
在今天的...
Right? And we can't imagine
that
...
black is good, white is bad.
黑色是...
Right? But in their culture, that's exactly what they believe.
??
Okay? Black did not mean death or the underworld.
...
It was the color of fertility.
它是...
The color of damp caves and rich soil,
...
of the womb of the goddess where life begins.
女神之胎中孕育之地的颜色。
White, on the other hand, was the color of death, of bones.
白色则是骨骿之色。
Okay? Does that make sense? So back then,
...??...??????...???
for most of human history, we thought
...????????????????
that white was bad
白色是好的，因其象征生命；白色则是好的！
because it symbolized death, and black was good because it symbolized life.
白色…………
And we can't possibly imagine that today, right?
翻译1
Okay? The last thing I want to talk about, and this is actually the most controversial thing, is,
翻译2
back then, for most of human history,
回到那时，几乎人类的历史里，
woman had power and agency.
女 人 的 身 体 可 可 可 可 …
Okay? What I mean by that is, back then,
OK? 先前的“前”??…
a woman's body was her body.
一位女性的身体就是她自己的身体。
She could choose to do whatever she wants with her body.
她可以选择自己想要的方式去使用它。
Does that make sense? In today's world,
...
if you get married, right, if a woman gets married,
then we assume the woman's body belongs to the husband.
然后我们把女性的身体归于丈夫。
Only the husband can sleep with her.
只有 只 只…
Okay? Does that make sense? But for most of human history,
好的？这有道理吗？但在大多数人类历史中，
this was not true.
这才是…
All right. So,
...
you look at sexual taboos today.
Okay? What are the sexual taboos to shame woman into proper behavior?
OK? 先后…
Okay? So, for example, okay,
?
if a man sleeps with a thousand women,
如果一个男人和千名女子同寝，我们认为他很帅。
we think, great, he's a stud.
如果一个男人与千名女子同寝，我们会好像…
He's good looking, he's rich, he's tall.
他好看又富有，身高身高！
He's a stud. He's a stud, right? But, hey,
他好看又富有…………………
if a woman sleeps with a thousand men, she's a slut.
他好…………………??
She's a bad person.
她是个坏人。
She has no ethical,
她有点儿…
she lacks ethics.
她缺少…
She lacks morality. She has no character.
她有点儿…
Therefore, we must avoid her.
他好…………………
Okay? Why does this make any logical sense?
...
Why is this true? Guys,
为什么这句...
why is this true? Okay?
为什么...
Yeah? How do you think about this?
...
Do you think that
你认为这件事…
this taboo is like something
这件事…
that's going to
这件…
force women to control women?
Exactly. We have this, okay?
We have this prejudice because
???
men are considered superior to women and therefore
men ... .. .. .. .. .. .. ... .. .. .. ... .. .. c….. .. …….. .. .. .. .. ?….. ?….. …………………………
men want to to control women and
? …….. ….. ……….. ………………..……..………………………………………………
the best way to do that
…….. .. ..…….. ….. men….. ..…..…..…..………………..…..…..…..………..……..………..……..
is by controlling the woman's body it doesn't make sense okay
is by controlling the woman'sbody it doesn't make sense okay
so this is just a cultural prejudice there's no
...
biological evidence this is true okay all right so
]}??
we have
...
a lot of evidence that
woman want sexual agency okay
...
women won't have sex there's nothing wrong with
女人不会有性事，没什么好说的
that okay so for example we look at monkeys Reese's monkeys
translations
and
females will aggressively seek males out for sex okay
females...
so it's the females that
...
are proactive you also look at Bonobos monkeys okay
是主动的，你也可以看看狒猴，好的
and Bonobos monkeys it's interesting because they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very
是...
aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and
???
they're very aggressive and
]}We need to translate cues 641 and 642. They are repeated phrases. We need toproduce Chinese translations. Use preferred terms? Not needed. Just translate
they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive aggressive and
]}We need………………………………………………………??…..??…………………………………………………………………………………
they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive aggressive and
...
they're very aggressive
??
and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and
]
they're very aggressive aggressive and they're very aggressive
and they're very aggressive and
and they're veryaggressive and
they're very initiate the sex.
There are some cultures where
有些文化中，
it's the female that
它是...
will initiate the sex with the male.
它...
So at Harvard and
在哈佛和UCLA发现了
UCLA they discovered
在哈佛和UCLA里发现了
the plow agriculture,
...
these societies have lower levels of female participation in politics
and the labor force. Meaning like before
???
where men and women did the same work,
both had the same political power.
两者同有政治权力。
But once men showed
that they could contribute more to society, men started to have more power.
...
Does that make sense? So in other words,
differences between men
...
and women are not biological
??
constructs, they are cultural constructs.
构造物， 其 简 原 ? ???? ?? ?? ?? ?? ！
And for most of human history, men and women were equal.
...
Any questions so far? Okay.
任何问题吗？
The idea of black and white, it's like white is good, black is bad.
...
It's a recent construct, okay?
它是最近的构造，好的？
It comes from the idea of race.
它从...
Okay? And race was invented about 20 years ago.
好的？种族在大约二十年前被发明？
Why? Because Europe was going around conquering the world
]}We need to translate cue [671] and [672] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations in order. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use terms:
and they needed to justify why they were doing this.
和...??
And the theory is because we're superior people.
...
Our race is better than your race.
我们的种族比你的种族更好。
Does that make sense? So race is a recent cultural construct.
它们的...
And it was to justify imperialism,
...
the conquest of other people, for no reason, right?
Does it make sense? So, all this is recent, okay?
它是否有意义？所以，全部这件事都已是最近的，好吗？
Alright, there's a really fun book called, sexual dawn, by Christopher Ryan, okay?
好的，...
And what he argues is that, for most of human history,
当且...
women had sexual agency, and
...
they They had multiple sexual partners.
And one piece of evidence is this.
...
Gorillas, right, they're the biggest primates.
They're huge, right? Well,
...
it turns out their penises, when
它们的阴茬在完全勃起时只有四厘米，OK？
fully erect, is only four centimeters, okay?
它们的...??????????????????????????????????????????
Men, who are a lot smaller than gorillas,
]}{
when erect,
当时...
they are at least almost four
...
times as big as the gorilla penises, okay?
So the question then is, why is this the case?
...
And one theory is
that when
...
women have multiple sexual partners,
女性有多重的...??
the man with the bigger penis
?
will spread his gene forward.
将会把他的基因向前传播。
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
那会让他...??
And so this is evidence that
并且如此，这就是证据，为大多数人类历史中，女性有多重…
for most of human history, women have had multiple sexual partners.
并且...
Okay? Okay.
好的，...??
So even when women had partners,
...
okay, a husband, they still had sexual partners, okay?
好的，丈夫们，仍然有了…
And in some societies, women have many husbands.
在某些社会里…
Usually brothers together, okay?
通常兄弟在一起，好吗？
All right, let me ask you this question.
好的，先给我来个问句吧。
Why do they do this?
为什么他们这么做？
Right? Because we've been taught this.
对了吧？那是因为我们已经学会了。
We've been taught, okay, we exist to spread our genes.
我们已经学会了…好吧！
Right? You understand?
好的，懂了！
So if I marry someone,
只要我先前往…
only if I'm sure
...
that the offspring, the children are mine,
翻译
will I work hard to ensure
Will ... ? ? ???? ... ? 译 ?? ???
that the children are fed
...
and raised properly and educated, okay?
Does that make sense? So we've been taught for a long time
...
that we first care about our genes, okay?
That's why men want to have as many wives
...
and children as possible, and
和孩子们一起，可能也会有…
women want to find the wealthiest husband.
女 好 好 …
But before most of human history, this was not the case.
但在大多数人类历史之前，这才是…
This was not true. Why?
...
Why, guys? Okay,
为什么呢，大家好！
so it has to do with the idea of religion, okay?
好吧！
So the first thing is that
So the first…
we all come from the mother goddess.
...
We're all equal, right?
我们都一样啦！
So it doesn't matter if my, if,
我们好像…
it doesn't matter if it's my son or my friend's son.
...
They're all the children of the mother goddess, and therefore
他们都...??
I have responsibility to protect the children, okay?
?
Does that make sense? So
??
there is no concept of individual.
735. 这里有个“个体”概念吗？
There's only a concept of community, okay?
?
That's the first thing. Second thing is they really didn't understand genes,
okay? They didn't understand like, okay,
好的？他们没理解，好像，好的，
a child, a woman, a child.
一个孩子，一个女人，一个孩子。
A woman has 50% genes from the mother, 50% genes from the father, okay?
一个女人有50%基因从母亲，50%基因从父亲，好吗？
How they understood was, okay,
他们是怎么理解的，好的，你有女人，女方给生命。男方给能量。
you have the woman, she gives life.
他们的理解是：好，先前方有个“女方”给生命。男方给能量。
The man gives energy.
先前方……
Okay, does that make sense? Therefore what?
OK? 这句 ? …
If you believe this, then what?
如果你先前方...
If the mother gives life,
...
the man gives energy, what?
男方给能量，什么？
What? Better energy to get better.
什么？更好能量到得更好。
Right, but how would you get better energy?
先前方……
More men, right?
先前方…
You understand? If men are giving you energy,
你知道吗？如果先前方…
the more men you have sex with, the more energy you have. Does that make sense?
...
So, the man gives you energy. The evidence is, if you look at the people in Melanesia,
所以，男人给你能量。证据是，若你看在美拉尼西亚的人们，
they believe that semen provided energy.
它们在此处…
And so you need a lot of semen.
...
So what would happen is that
when a woman married a husband,
当一个女人嫁给丈夫时，
what would happen is the members of the husband's family would come
当时…
and have sex with her that
和他一起…
very night in order to get as much energy as possible from the family.
很久…
Does it make sense, guys? Okay?
...
Any questions so far?
I know this is controversial, but
...
I'm just trying to show you how our cultural
beliefs is radically different from the cultural beliefs of people in the past.
信仰与过去人们的文化信仰截然不同。
Okay, does it make sense?
好的，能理解吗？
Okay, so one last piece of evidence is this.
好的，最后一块证据是这件…
When you don't know
当你不知道
who your,
你的人，
when the people don't know who the father is,
当…
everyone has a responsibility to protect the child.
每个人都有责任去照顾孩子。
Okay, does that make sense to you guys?
好的，能给我方块？
Okay? So the story is this Christian missionary,
好的，...
he goes into a village and
他去到一个村庄里，他发现人们正好睡着相互相。
he finds people just sleeping with each other, okay?
他在村里找到了睡眠的相互。
There's no marriage, there's no husband and wife.
他在村里找到了睡眠相互。”
People are just sleeping with each other.
And the priest says to them, you people are shameless.
翻译1
And one of the villagers replies,
翻译2
you have no sense.
...
You French people love only your own children,
but we all love all the children of our tribe.
但我们都爱我们部落的所有孩子。
Okay? You understand?
好的，先前?
So having multiple sexual partners is a way to build community for everyone.
有多位配偶者是为大家建群的好方法。
If you're a small community, okay, maybe 15,
如果是小型群体，...
20 people, it makes sense to make sure that
20人，先前好吧！
everyone loves each other and everyone will protect all the children.
20个………………
Does it make sense guys? All right, so
788 译文1
let me tell you a story to illustrate this fact.
788 译前后?
We know that in World War II, okay,
我们知道在第二次世界大战里，
in World War II, American pilots, okay,
我们知道在第二次世界大战里…
what they were doing for,
他们正在做的事情是……
what they were doing is they were sleeping with each other's wife,
他睡眠……
okay?
...
Does that make sense? The reason why they were doing this is
American pilots were more likely to die in war
...
than any other soldiers.
Does that make sense guys? Therefore,
在此处...???
you slept with the wife of your colleagues
]}We need to produce translations for cues 798-800. Provide JSON array translations. Each stringmay contain at most one newline. Use Chinese terms. Let's translate each cue in order. Cue 798:
in order to ensure that if you die,
]}We need to produce translations for cues 798-800. Provide JSON array translations. Each string may contain at most one newline. Use... Wait we need to produce translations for cues 798-800. Let's produce array of 3 translations. Use Chinese. Let's craft. Cue 798:
they would protect your children.
他们会照顾你的孩子们。
Because there's a good chance you would die in war, okay?
因为有很大机会你会在战场上丢命，好的？
You were afraid that if I died, who's going to look after my wife and who's going to look after my children?
我怕如果我丢命，谁来照顾我的妻子和孩子们？
And the way you build intimacy
]?..?????..??..?????..?????..??..?????..??..?????..??..??..??..???..??..?????..??…..??..??..???…..??…..??…..??…..??…..??…..??..???…..??…..??….. …… ……? ? ? … ??… … … … ??… … … … … … i…..??..… … … ..??… … ??… … ...??… … ..??… … ??… ..…… … ..… … … ..… …… …… …… …… …… …… … … i…..??… … ..… ..… … ..… … ..…
and community is by sleeping with each other's wife.
...
So you became one big family.
Okay? Does that make sense guys?
好的？这有道理吗，大家好？
Any questions so far? Okay, so let's go to the next slide.
接下来…
Okay, so let's go to the next slide.
好的，接下来我们来看看下一张幻灯片。
I know this is controversial, I know this is hard to understand, okay?
我知道这很有争议，能否给我方位？
But we have evidence that
翻译1
for most of human history,
翻译2
woman had sexual agency
女 好 好 ...
and power, and sex was a way to build community,
...
okay? Does that make sense?
好的？那算得通吗？
Yeah? I think this idea is pretty much not true.
是的，嗯？我觉得这点儿很久…
Okay? But I think it's true. But
好的？但我觉得是个好点儿。
you can use it as a factor compared to the.
你可以把它作为一个相对的因素
I mean, I already said it's true that
我想说…………………………………………………
the idea is that you are,
?
but using it as a factor to,
…………………………………………………
to keep, using it as a factor to
翻译1
to carry on. Okay.
]}
So that's the question, okay? So the question is,
?
is this backwards or is it primitive?
是这回向还是原始？
Okay. And what I want to show you this semester is that,
好的，先前我想要给你们本学期展示的就是
okay, guys, there's no such concept as backward and primitive, okay?
好的，先前…
The reason why we care about sex more than any other people
...
is the idea of private property, okay?
Private property.
...
Okay? So for example, if I have a wife,
好的？比如说，我有一位妻子，
I do have a wife, okay?
我有个妻子，好的？
We have three kids, okay?
我们有三位孩子，好的？
I want my three kids to inherit the money.
我想让我的三个孩子继承这笔钱。
Right? But
右？但
if my wife goes to sleep with other people,
如果我妻子和别人同睡，
then who gets the private property?
翻译1
So in other words,
翻译2
we have the idea of sex as shameful
翻译?
because we live in a private, we live in a patriarchy.
因为我们在私有里生活，...
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
...
Okay. Sorry. Let me explain some more later on, okay?
All right. Let's move on.
We have...?
All right. So I want to conclude with this idea.
All right. So I want toconclude with this idea.
I want to conclude Maria Gumbutas argued
..
that old Europe was ruled by women or women were part of the political class.
那时的欧洲由女性统治，或女性是政治阶层的一部分。
And because of that, Europe,
欧洲之所以有此种情况，因其…
at that time, was more peaceful and more stable
在那时，...更好？
than at any other time in its history.
...
Does that make sense? So another question then is,
在这句里，能否给我一句翻译？
why would women as a political class
?
be more effective than men as a political class?
...
Okay? And there are three reasons. All right?
The first reason is
第一个原因是
women are more willing to cooperate and collaborate.
女性更愿意合作与协作。
It doesn't make sense.
它不太对劲。
So men are competitive.
它们的竞争性很大
We like status.
我们喜欢地位。
We like power. But women are much more humble.
我们喜欢地位。??
So women are much more likely to compromise
{
and collaborate than men are.
和……更愿意合作与协作。
Okay? Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
好的？ 这算是吗？
So if men are in control, then men want all the power.
如果男士在控制之下，...
But if women are in control, then
但如果女士掌控之时，...
women are much more willing to share power with men.
…….. … … …
Does that make sense? The other thing is,
….. … 女性 … ..
let's just say, like, your community gets in conflict with another community. Well,
让我们说个例子：你们的群体与另一群体冲突时，
what would happen is the women leaders of your community would get together with the women leaders of
该群体的女领袖们会与我们群体的女领袖们一起聚集，
that community and you could quickly negotiate a compromise.
随后可快速协商达成协议。
Right? But men are competitive.
??
They like status. They like face.
他们喜欢 … ?? ?? ???? ?? ?? ... ?
So it's much more likely
...
that when men start to negotiate,
当男人开始谈判时，
it becomes violent.
当时…
Does that make sense? Okay?
那算得了吗？好的？
So that's one thing that women are better at.
于是这就是一条好事。”
Women are better at collaborating and compromising.
女性更擅长协作与妥协。
That's the first thing. Second thing is
that women have more emotional intelligence.
那时…
Does that make sense, guys? Meaning, like,
]}
men care about rules.
男士关心规则。
Right? Women care more about you as a person.
男士们关心规则。
Therefore, women are much better
因此，女性更擅长管理人。
at managing people.
Does that make sense? Okay?
那时…
The third thing is that
】
men can use violence to coerce other people.
男士关心规则。
Women are not as physically strong as men.
女 ... ... ... …
Therefore, they have other strategies for controlling men.
? ????…
And the two main strategies are
]
gossip, okay? Basically talking about you behind your back,
咱们说说咱们的咱们…
which forces you to conform.
咱...…
But also sex. Okay?
So if the woman spreads sex evenly
如果女人把性散在各个男人身上，男人们就没有理由去争斗。
among the men, the men have no reason to fight.
如果人们把性散在各个……
And if someone, the man, does something bad against the community,
...
the woman can choose to not have sex with this man.
Okay? As a way to punish him.
OK? 作为一种给他打击打击…
But this is all very subtle
...
and nonviolent ways of forcing people to conform
并且以非暴力方式强迫人们顺从社会规则。
to the rules of the society.
并且以非暴力方式强迫人们…
Okay? Okay?
好的？好的？
Does that make sense? Any questions?
那能理解吗？有点儿…
This is confusing to you guys, right?
这对你们来说很有点儿…
Okay? So, let's conclude, okay?
OK?…
Before the conquest of the Yamaya,
在征服雅马雅之前，
all Europe was a peaceful
egalitarian society. Okay?
...
And a lot of the reason why is that
women were given higher status in society.
女性在社会中获得更高的地位。
So it was women who made the rules and the rules of the society and the rules of the society.
于是，女性制定了社会的规则与制度。
who were the most powerful and the most powerful in the society.
谁是最强大的?
And because of that, women are able to use
...
nonviolent ways to control society.
Making society much more peaceful and stable.
让社会更安定与和平。
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
好的？这句算是说好的吗？
Any questions?
还有什么？
Excuse me? Okay, okay.
请问一下？好的，好的。
So the question then, the question is,
...
if people are not violent,
how do you control society? Okay?
怎么控制社会？好的吗？
And so, the way you can control people is by,
那么，控制人们的方式是通过……
is through the idea of shame.
通过羞愧的概念来。”
Okay? Because everyone wants to get along.
好的？因为大家都想顺利进行。
Okay? All right.
好的？一切都好。
So, all right.
好的，全部好。
Here's a fun experiment. Okay?
...
Here's a fun experiment. What you guys can do is,
every time you walk the hallways
...
and you see a person wearing red,
like a girl wearing red, you tell her, you look fantastic.
...
Okay? I guarantee you,
within like two weeks, all the girls in the school will be wearing red.
在 里 里 里...??
Does that make sense? So you're controlling people,
...
but you're not using violence.
translations
You're using the idea of gossip,
]}We need to translate cues 935 and 936. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure Chinese. Use terms. Provide two translations. Let's craft. 935:
shame, and flattery.
羞愧，和奉承。
And that's what women do really well.
而这正是女子们真正擅长的事。
Do you understand? Okay?
...
Does that answer your question?
Okay. Any more questions?
好的。还有问题吗？
Yeah, so you don't have to use violence.
好的，接下来我们要看雅姆纳雅人。
You can also use flattery.
你也可以用奉承。
Okay? Right?
好的？
Any more questions?
好的吗？
Okay. So,
好的。接下来我们要看雅姆纳雅人。
next class, what we'll do is we'll look at the Yamnaya people.
好的，接下来...
Okay? Because the Yamnaya people are violent.
好的？因为雅姆纳雅人很暴力。
They love war. They're patriarchy.
他们很久的战事。
And they have private property.
...
The question then is, okay, how do they come about?
第几句？ 这就是...
Okay? What's their origin story?
...
And why would they come about? Why were they so successful in conquering old Europe?
Okay? So that's a story we will look at next class.
...